Scripting the Vim editor, PartEvent5:-driven scripting and automation
Automate your workflow with Vim’s autocommands

Some practical examples

Managing simultaneous edits
---------------------------

One of the most useful features of Vim is that it automatically detects when you attempt a file that is currently being edited by some other instance of Vim. That often happens i window environments, where you’re already editing a file in another terminal; or in multi setups, where someone else is already working on a shared file. When Vim detects a second attempt to edit a particular file, you get the following request:

Swap file ".filename.swp" already exists!

[O]pen Read-Only, (E)dit anyway, (R)ecover, (Q)uit, (A)bort: _

Depending on the environment in which you’re working, your fingers probably automatically one of those options every time, without much conscious thought on your part. For example rarely work on shared files, you probablyq justtoterminatehit the session, and then go hunting
for the terminal window where you’re already editing the file. On the other hand, if you shared resources, perhaps your fingers are trained to immediately<ENTER>hit, in order to select
the default option and open the file read-only.

With autocommands, however, you can completely eliminate the need to see, recognize, and respond to that message, simply by automating the responseSwapExists event that triggers
it. For example, if you never want to edit files that are already being edited elsewhere, add the following to .vimrc:

Listing 9. Automatically quitting on simultaneous edits

augroup NoSimultaneousEdits
autocmd!
     autocmd SwapExists * :let v:swapchoice = 'q' 
augroup END

It then installs a handler SwapExists event on any file (using the universal fil pattern:*). That handler simply assigns the response'q'to the specialv:swapchoice variable.

Vim consults this variable prior to displayingswapfile exists"message. If the variable has been set, it uses the value as the automatic response and doesn’t bother showing the mess So now you’ll never see swapfile message; your Vim session will just automatically quit i try to edit a file that’s being edited elsewhere.

Alternately, if you’d prefer always to open already edited files in read-only mode, you c change theNoSimultaneousEdits group to:

Listing 10. Automating read-only access to existing files

augroup NoSimultaneousEdits autocmd!
     autocmd SwapExists * :let v:swapchoice = 'o' 
augroup END

More interestingly, you could arrange to select between these two (or any other) alternat based on the location of the file being considered. For example, you might prefer to auto in your own subdirectories, but open shared files/dev/shared/ as read-only. You could do that with the following:

Listing 11. Automating a context-sensitive response

augroupNoSimultaneousEdits
autocmd!
autocmdSwapExists~/*:let v:swapchoice = 'q'
  autocmdSwapExists/dev/shared/*:let v:swapchoice = 'o'
augroupEND

That is: if the full filename begins with the home directory, followed by~/*anything),then at all preselect the "quit" behaviour; but if the full filename starts with the/dev/shared/directory *), then preselect the "read-only" behaviour instead.

Autoformatting code consistently
--------------------------------
For example, you could add the following autocommand group .vimrc , so that C, Python, Perl, and XML files are automatically run through the appropriate code formatter whenever open a file of the corresponding type, as shown in Listing 12.

Listing 12. Beautiful code, on autocommand

augroup CodeFormatters
autocmd!
autocmdBufReadPost,FileReadPost*.py:silent %!PythonTidy.py
autocmdBufReadPost,FileReadPost*.p[lm]:silent %!perltidy -q
autocmdBufReadPost,FileReadPost*.xml:silent %!xmlpp –t –c –n
autocmdBufReadPost,FileReadPost*.[ch]:silent %!indent
augroup END

In this case, the events listed for each   BufReadPost (which is queued whenever an
existing file is loaded into a new buffer)FileReadPost (which is queued immediately after any :read command is executed). These two events are often specified together because between them they cover the most common ways of loading the contents of an existing file into a b
After the event list, each autocommand specifies the file suffix(es) to which it applies:

.py, Perl’s.pl and .pm, XML’s.xml, or the.c and .h files of C. Note that, as with events, these filename patterns could also have been specified as a comma-separated list, rather than a pattern. For example, the Perl handler could have been written:

autocmd	BufReadPost,FileReadPost   *.pl,*.pm   :silent %!perltidy -q

or the C handler could be extended to handle common C++ variants.C,.cc,.cxx, etc.) as well, like so:

autocmd	BufReadPost,FileReadPost   *.[chCH],*.cc,*.hh,*.[ch]xx  :silent %!indent

As usual, the final component of each autocommand is the command to be executed. In each case, it is a global filter %!filter_program ), which takes the entire contents of the fi (%) and pipes it out!) to( the specified external program PythonTidy.py,perltidy,xmlpp,
or indent). The output of each program is then pasted back into the buffer, replacing the contents.
Normally, when filter commands like these are used, Vim automatically displays a notifica the command completes, like so:

42 lines filtered

Press ENTER or type command to continue_

To prevent this annoyance, each of the autocommands prefixes its action:silentwith, whicha neutralizes any ordinary information messages, but still allows error messages to be disp

Opportunistic code autoformatting

The simplest approach is to make use ofInsertLeave event. This event is queued whenever you exit fromInsert mode (most commonly, immediately after you<ESC>). You can easily set up a handler that reformats your code every time you finish adding to it, like so:

Listing 13. Invoking PerlTidy after every edit

function! TidyAndResetCursor ()
let cursor_pos = getpos('.') %!perltidy -q
     call setpos('.', cursor_pos) endfunction

augroup PerlTidy
autocmd!
     autocmd InsertLeave *.p[lm] :call TidyAndResetCursor() 
augroup END

The TidyAndResetCursor() function first makes a record of the current cursor position, by the cursor information returned by the getpos()in in the variablecursor_pos. It then runs the externalperltidy utility over the entire%!perltidy -q), and finally restores the cursor to it original position, by passing the saved cursor information tosetpos()builtfunction-in.

Inside thePerlTidy group, you then just set up a single autocommand that calls TidyAndResetCursor() every time the user leavesInsert mode within any Perl file.

This same code pattern could be adapted to perform any appropriate action each time you i text. For example, if you were working on a very unreliable system and wished to maximize ability to recover files:help usr_11.txt) if something went wrong, you could arrange for Vi to update its swap-file every time Insertleftmode, like so:

augroup UpdateSwap
autocmd!
     autocmd InsertLeave * :preserve
augroup END

Timestamping files

Another useful set of eventsBufWritePre,FileWritePre, andFileAppendPre. These Pre"

events are queued just before your Vim session writes a buffer back to disk (as a result command such as :write,:update, or:saveas ). ABufWritePre event occurs just before the entire buffer is written,FileWritePre occurs just before part of a buffer is written (that is, when specify a range of lines to be :1,10write). AFileAppendPre occurs just before:write

command is used to append rather than replace; for example:

:write >> logfile.log).

For all three types of events, Vim sets the special line-number'[andaliases']to the range

of lines being written. These aliases can then be used in the range specifier of any subs command, to ensure that autocommand actions are applied only to the relevant lines.

Typically, you would set up a single handler that covered all three types of pre-writing example, you could have Vim automatically update an internal timestamp whenever a file wa written (or appended) to disk, as shown in Listing 14.

Listing 14. Automatically updating an internal timestamp whenever a fil saved

function! UpdateTimestamp ()
     '[,']s/^This file last updated: \zs.*/\= strftime("%c") 
/ endfunction

augroup TimeStamping
autocmd!
autocmd BufWritePre,FileWritePre,FileAppendPre * :call UpdateTimestamp() 
augroup END

The UpdateTimestamp() function performs a substitutions/.../.../ ) on every line being written, by specifically limiting the range of the substitution'[ toandbetween']like so:'[,']s/.../.../.
The substitution looks for lines startingThis file last updated:”, followed by anything

(.*). The\zs before the.* causes the substitution to pretend that the match only started af colon, so only the actual timestamp is replaced.

To update the timestamp, the substitution uses the\= escape sequence in the replacement text. This escape sequence tells Vim to treat the replacement text as a Vimscript express evaluating it to get the actual replacement string. In this case, that expression is a ca built-strftime() function, which returns a standard timestamp string ofFri Octform: "
23 14:51:01 2009". This string is then written back into the timestamp line by the substit command.


All that remains is to set up an event autocmd) (for all three event types (BufWritePre,FileWritePre,FileAppendPre) in any file*) and( have it invoke the appropriate timestamping function:call UpdateTimestamp()). Now, any time a file is written, any timesta in the lines being saved will be updated to the current time.

Note that Vim provides two other sets of events that you can use to modify the behavior o operations. To automate some action that should happen after a write, BufWritePost , FileWritePost, andFileAppendPost. To completely replace the standard write behavior with yo own script, you can BufWriteCmd,FileWriteCmd, andFileAppendCmd (but consult:help Cmd-

event first for some important caveats).

Table-driven timestamps

Of course, you could also create much more elaborate mechanisms to handle files with diff timestamping conventions. For example, you might prefer to specify the various timestamp signatures and their replacements in a Vim dictionary (see the previous article in this s then loop through each pair to determine how the timestamp should be updated. This approa shown in Listing 15.

Listing 15. Table-driven automatic timestamps

let s:timestamps ={
\'Thisfilelastupdated: \zs.*':'strftime("%c")',
\'Lastmodification: \zs.*':'strftime("%Y%m%d.%H%M%S")',
\'Copyright(c) .\{-}, \d\d\d\d-\zs\d\d\d\d' :'strftime("%Y")',
\}

function! UpdateTimestamp ()

for [signature, replacement] in items(s:timestamps)
     silent! execute "'[,']s/" . signature . '/\= ' . replacement . 
     '/' endfor
endfunction

Here, the for loop iterates through each timestamp’s signature/replacement pair in the s:timestamps dictionary, like so:

for [signature, replacement] in items(s:timestamps)

It then generates a string containing the corresponding substitution command. The followi substitution command is identical in structure to the one in the previous example, but is constructed by interpolating the signature/replacement pair into a string:

"'[,']s/" . signature . '/\= ' . replacement . '/'

Finally, it executes the generated command silently:

silent! execute "'[,']s/" . signature . '/\= ' . replacement . '/'

The use ofsilent! is important because it ensures that any substitutions that don’t match result in the annoyingPattern not found error message.


Note that the last entrys:timestamps is a particularly useful example: it automatically upda the year-range of any embedded copyright notices, whenever a file containing them is writ

Filename-driven timestamps

Instead of listing all possible timestamp formats in a single table, you might prefer to theUpdateTimestamp() function and then create a series of autocmds for different filetypes, as shown in Listing 16.

Listing 16. Context-sensitive timestaming for different filetypes

function! UpdateTimestamp (signature, replacement)silent! execute "'[,']s/" . a:signature . '/\= ' . a:replacement . '/'
endfunction

augroup Timestamping autocmd!

" Cheader files use one timestamp format ... autocmd BufWritePre,FileWritePre,FileAppendPre  *.h\ :call UpdateTimestamp('This file last updated: \zs.*', 'strftime("%c")')" C code files useanother ...autocmd BufWritePre,FileWritePre,FileAppendPre  *.c\ :call UpdateTimestamp('Last update: \zs.*', 'strftime("%Y%m%d.%H%M%S")')
augroupEND

In this version, the signature and replacement components are passed explicitly to UpdateTimestamp(), which then generates a string containing the single corresponding substitution command and executes it. WithinTimestamping group, you then set up individual autocommands for each required file type, passing the appropriate timestamp signature and replacement text for each.

Conjuring directories

Autocommands can be useful even before you begin editing. For example, when you start edi a new file, you will occasionally see a message like this one:

"dir/subdir/filename" [New DIRECTORY]

Thismeans that thefile you specified (infilenamecase) does not exist and that the directoryit’ssupposed to bein (in thisdir/subdir) doesn’t exist either.
Vim will happily allow you to ignore this warning (many users don’t even recognize that i warning) and continue to edit the file. But when you try to save it you’ll be confronted following unhelpful error message:

"dir/subdir/filename" E212: Can't open file for writing.

Now, in order to save your work, you have to explicitly create the missing directory befo the file into it. You can do that from within Vim like so:

:write
"dir/subdir/filename" E212: Can't open file for 
writing. :call mkdir(expand("%:h"),"p")
:write

Here, the call to the expand() function is applied"%:h" , where the% means the current filepath (in this dir/subdir/filename), and the:h takes just the "head" of that path, removi the filename to leave the path of the intended dir/subdir )(. The call to Vim’s built-in mkdir() then takes this directory path and creates all the interim directories along it ( by the second argument,"p").

Realistically, though, most Vim users would be more likely to simply escape to the shell necessary directories. For example:

:write
"dir/subdir/filename" E212: Can't open file for writing.
:! mkdir -p dir/subdir/
:write

Either way, it’s a hassle. If you’re eventually going to have to create the missing direc why not have Vim notice up-front that it doesn’t exist, and simply create it for you befo start? That way, you’ll never encounter the New DIRECTORY] hint; nor will your workflow b later interrupted by an equally mysteriousE212error.

To have Vim take care of prebuilding non-existent directories, you could hook a handler i BufNewFile event, which is queued whenever you start to edit a file that does not yet exi 17 shows the code you would add to .vimrc file to make this work.

Listing 17. Unconditionally autocreating non-existent directories

augroup AutoMkdir autocmd!
     autocmd BufNewFile * :call EnsureDirExists() augroup END
function! EnsureDirExists ()
let required_dir = expand("%:h") if !isdirectory(required_dir)
     call mkdir(required_dir, 'p') endif
endfunction

The AutoMkdir group sets up a single autocommandBufNewFile events on any kind of file, callingEnsureDirExists() function whenever a new file is EnsureDirExists()

first determines the directory being requested by expanding the "head"of the current file expand("%:h"). It then uses the builtisdirectory() function to check whether the requested directory exists. If not, it attempts to create the directory usingmkdir()Vim’s. built-in

Note that, if mkdir() call can’t create the requested directory for any reason, it will pr slightly more precise and informative error message:

E739: Cannot create directory: dir/subdir

Conjuring directories more carefully

The only problem with this solution is that, occasionally, autocreating non-existent subd exactly the wrong thing to do. For example, suppose you requested the following:


> vim /share/sites/corporate/root/.htaccess

You had intended to create a new access control file in the already existing/share/subdirectory corporate/website/root/. Except, of course, because you got the path wrong, what you actua did was create a new access control file in the formerly non-existent/share/website/ corporate/root/. And because that happened automatically, with no warnings of any kind, yo might not even realize the mistake. At least, not until the misapplied access control pre some online disaster.

To guard against errors like this, you might prefer that Vim be a little less helpful in missing directories. Listing 18 shows a more elaborate EnsureDirExists(), which

still detects missing directories but now asks the user what to do about them. Note that autocommand set-up is exactly the same as in Listing 17;EnsureDirExists() function has changed.

Listing 18. Conditionally autocreating non-existent directories

augroup AutoMkdir autocmd!
     autocmd BufNewFile * :call EnsureDirExists()
augroup END
function! EnsureDirExists ()
let required_dir = expand("%:h") 
if !isdirectory(required_dir)
call AskQuit("Directory '" . required_dir . "' doesn't exist.", "&Create it?")
try
     call mkdir( required_dir, 'p' ) catch
     call AskQuit("Can't create '" . required_dir . "'", "&Continue anyway?") endtry
     endif
endfunction

function! AskQuit (msg, proposed_action)
if confirm(a:msg, "&Quit?\n" . a:proposed_action) == 1 exit
endif
endfunction

In this version of the function,EnsureDirExists() locates the required directory and detects whether it exists, exactly as before. However, if the directoryEnsureDirExists() now calls a helper function:AskQuit(). This function uses the confirm() function to inquire
whether you want to exit the session or autocreate the "Quit?"directoryis. presented as the first option, which also makes it the default if <ENTER>. hit

If you do select "Quit?"option, the helper function immediately terminates the Vim session Otherwise, the helper function simply returns. In EnsureDirExists() continues to

execute, and attempts to mkdir().

Note, however, that the callmkdir() is now insidetry...endtry construct. This is -- as you might expect -- an exception handler, which will now E739catcherrorthe that is thrownmkdir()
is unable to create the requested directory.


When that error is thrown,catch block will intercept it and AskQuit()callagain, informing

you that the directory could not be created, and asking whether you still want to continu details on Vim’s extensive exception handling mechanisms:help exception-handling.

The overall effect of this second versionEnsureDirExists() is to highlight the non-existent directory but require you to explicitly request that it be created (by‘c’typiwheng a single prompted to). If the directory cannot be created, you are again warned and given the opti continuing with the session anyway (again, by typing'c' singlewhenasked). This also makes it trivially easy to escape from a mistaken edit (simply<ENTER>hittoingselect the default"Quit?" option at either prompt).

Of course, you might prefer that continuing was the default, in which case, you would jus the first lineAskQuit() to:

if confirm(a:msg, a:proposed_action . "\n&Quit?") == 2

In this case the proposed action would be the first alternative, and hence the default be Note that"Quit?" is now the second alternative, so the response now has to be compared aga the value 2.
